Guide to the Puebla Archives
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Puebla archives
1567-1904
MS 1979
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
24.75
(50 boxes)
The collection comprises legal manuscripts relating to church and state affairs of the Mexican state of Puebla.
Deacon, John, 17th century
General
Puebla Archives was originally part of the Latin American Manuscript Collection (MS 307).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired in exchange with Lindley E. Eberstadt, 1948.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Registers and Lists, 1614-1898. II. Criminal Cases, 1570-1904. III. Civil Cases, 1567-1878. IV. Miscellaneous Records, 1594-1901. Series are arranged chronologically therein.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Puebla Archives consist of legal manuscripts relating to the church and state affairs of the Mexican state of Puebla covering the years 1567-1904. The state capital, also called Puebla, is one of the oldest and most picturesque cities of Mexico. In 1537, the Jesuits founded the College of the Holy Ghost, which is now a university. Puebla is known as a city of churches and has an outstanding ancient cathedral constructed between 1552 and 1649. A theater, built in 1790, is claimed to be the oldest on the continent. The state of Puebla is largely mountainous (average altitude 7000 feet) and occupies part of the central portion of the Mexican plateau. Across the center extends the volcanic belt, which includes on Puebla's border three of the highest peaks in Mexico: Pico de Orizaba, Popocatepetl, and Ixtachihuatl. Primarily an agricultural area, there is some mining of gold, silver, and copper. The state contains many archaeological sites of pre-Columbian and pre-Aztec origin; the most famous is the Pyramid of Cholula.
Major and minor events in the history of Puebla are recorded in the manuscripts. Subjects documented include: estate claims; reorganization of the postal system; a prison escape; bondsmen and loans; colonial, state, and national taxes and customs duties; election of Indians to local government posts; violent domestic relations including adultery, concubines, incest, maltreatment and drunkenness; pulquerias and pulque (a fermented drink) sales; treatment of Indians; governmental orders and directives; proceedings of criminal and civil cases; land and water rights; hacienda livestock; and the health system.
Tobacco use -- Early works to 1800; Tobacco tortured; Filthie fume of tobacco refined
- Registers and Lists, 1614-1898; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  .
  - Register of proxies, 1614 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Register of cases brought before the court, 1765-1789 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - List of receipts of inventories, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Register of branding and blacksmiths' licenses, 1788 - 1811 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Record of provincial meetings of the court clerk, 1794 - 1796 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - List of criminal cases brought tbefore the Tribunal of the Governor, 1801 - 1815 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Register of wills, foundations of chaplaincies and other civil matters, 1801 - 1858 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Register of entries of the Public Office, 1803 - 1804 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Register of various matters brought before the court, 1804 - 1898 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Register of entries of the Public Office, 1805 - 1806 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - List of civil cases before the Intendant's Office, 1811 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - List of cases brought before the court, 1817 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Register of cases, submitted to the Superior Government, 1822 - 1827 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Register of judicial decisions, 1823 - 1830 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Register of criminal cases brought before the Superior Court, 1825 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - List of criminal cases sent to the State Attorney, 1825 - 1827 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - List of criminal cases brought before the Attorney, 1826 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - List of civil cases assigned to one of the offices, 1826 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - List of civil cases received by the second attorney, 1826 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Register of fines, 1826 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - List of civil cases received by the Attorney, 1826 - 1827 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - List of criminal cases brought before the court, 1827 - 1832 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - List of action concerning criminal cases considered at the Supreme Court, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - List of cases pending before the Higher Tribunal, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Register of civil cases brought before the court, 1831 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Register of criminal cases brought before the court, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Register of criminal cases brought before the second Tribunal, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - List of criminal cases brought before the Supreme Court, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Register of criminal cases brought before the second Tribunal, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - List of criminal cases brought before the court, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Records of the first Tribunal,Taxpan, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Record of the judicial decisions, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 31 A)
  - List of defendants in the second Criminal Tribunal, 1836 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - List of civil and criminal cases presented to the court on appeal from the justices, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Register of correspondence sent by the court, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Record of pensions paid, 1842 - 1843 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Record of judiciary events, paroles, citations, 1842 - 1844 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Register of cases presented to the courts, 1842 - 1845 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Records of the appointment of fiscal agents, 1842 - 1846 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Register of bonds and bondsmen tried at the Criminal court, 1843 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Register of bonds and bondsmen, 1843 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - List of slight misdemeanors judged, 1843-1845 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Register of bonds and bondsmen of criminals tried at court, 1844 - 1845 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - List of the criminal cases brought before the second Tribunal, Matamoros, 1846 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - 11th notebook of extra judicial acts, 1847 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Register of civil and criminal cases brought before the courts, 1850 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - List of civil cases presented to the court on appeal, 1855 - 1857 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Register of cases before the court, 1855 - 1857 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Register of the court of Zacapoaztla, 1858 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Register of decisions of the court, Acatlán, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - NO FOLDER # 50
- Criminal Cases, 1570-1904; Series II
  - Case against Francisco, for injuries, 1570 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Case against Antonio Lucas, for the theft of a horse, 1581 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Offices of the Royal Justice vs. Juan García Barranco, for locking up Indians, 1603 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Gregorio Barrientos vs. those accused of stealing a chestnut colored mare, 1605 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Jacobalinda vs. an Indian baker, concerning a sum of money, 1607 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Case against Gregorio García, 1609 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Magdalena María, Indian vs. Pedro deVillota, Spaniard, for mistreating and beating her, 1609 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Case against Diego de la Mata, for cohabitating with a married woman and, because of her, killing Alonso de la Puebla Denounced by Francisco Malgarejo, 1609 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Miguél Martín Monje vs. Julián Blas, French, for attempting to murder him, 1609 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Case against Gaspar de Rivera, for calumny of Juan Vega and Diego de la Cruz, 1613 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Case against Felipe de Herrera, for the murder of Bartolomé Gómez, 1620 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Case against Baltazar Rodriguez for concubinage, 1620 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Case against Isabel de Chávez, mestiza, for making pulque, 1621 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Case against Diego de Malpica for making yellow pulque, 1621 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Francisco de Soria vs. Fernando Manuel, Indian, 1621 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Office of the Royal Justice and Pedro Guillén de Saavedra vs. Joan Barranco and Cristóbal Barbero Sapado, 1621 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Francisco Alvarez Yañez vs. Joan Peréz, mestizo, for entering his house and cohabitating with his servant Ana María, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Francisco de Arellano vs. Matheo Díaz and Andrés Díaz, for beating him and injuring one hand, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Santos de Balbín vs. those accused of stealing a mule, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Alonso de Bocanegra vs. Pedro Cisneros, for injuries, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Melchor Collado vs.Simón Rodríguez Carnero, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Jerónimo Jiménez vs. Marcos de Sigura, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Case against Diego de Monroy and Pedro de la Barrera, for knifings, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Case against Alphonsa de la Our, Indian, for making white pulque, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Sebastiána de los Ríos, mestiza, vs. José de Aguilar, mestizo, for facial injuries, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Simón Rodríguez Carnero vs. Melchor Collado, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Case against Simón Rodríguez Carnero, Ventura Rodríguez, Francisco Ordoñez, and Martín de Oliveros, concerning pending litigation for knifing, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Office of the Royal Justice vs. the alleged murderer of Bernabé Sánchez, Spaniard, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Dispatch of the Office of Royal Justice concerning the death of Damian Cosme, Indian, 1623 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Case against Juan Velasquez, Indian, for theft of articles from the San Francisco Convent, 1628 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Domingo de Arruete vs. Joan Alonso Lotorrero, for insulting him and threatening to murder him, 1639 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Case against Nicolás Guillén, for concubinage, 1642 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Case against Juan Mexicano, mestizo, for concubinage, 1642 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Juan Pasqual vs. several accused of theft, 1642 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Office of Royal Justice vs. Alonso, mestizo, for injury to Juan Gutiérrez, mestizo, 1646 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Office of Royal Justice vs. Antonio Nicolás and Juan Bautista, Indian, for punching Miguél Solano, 1677 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Case against Pedro de Zamora, for the theft of a donkey, 1717 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Office of Royal Justice vs. Juan Moreno and Micaela de Mora, for incontinence, 1723 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Ana de Encarnación vs. Juan Francisco Hordoñez, her husband, 1724 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Case against Ambrosio Martínez, for injury to Juan de la Vega, 1725 - 1729 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Office of Royal Justice vs. Diego Jerónimo, Indian, for the death of Juan Cayetano, 1740 - 1744 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Josépha Gertrúdis, Indian vs. Francisco Peréz, mestizo, for attempting to rape her, 1745 - 1767 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Office of Royal Justice vs. Felipe de Córdova and his servant, Juan Pablo, for forgery, 1747 - 1750 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - María Gertrúdis de Alba vs. Jacinto López, her husband, for misconduct, 1757 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Esteban and Bernarda Antonio, Indians vs. Lorenzo Cuio, for injuries, 1757 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - María Astasia, Indian, vs. Manuel de la Cruz, her husband, for concubinage, 1757 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - María Gertrúdis de la Encarnación, Indian, vs. Juan Antonio Ramirez, for injuries, 1757 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Rita Gertrúdis, Indian vs. Diego Martín, her husband for concubinage, 1757 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Joséph Antonio Sosa vs. Francisco, for injuries, 1758 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Decree concerning defendants in prison for criminal offenses, 1770 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - María Joséfa Ortíz vs. José Manuel Viñas, her husband, for adultery, 1770 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Case against several for sedition, 1776 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Case against José Camacho, 1781 - 1785 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Case against María de la Luz Iglesias, for incontinence, 1784 - 1787 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Case against José Antonio Catano, for beating Manuel Sánchez, Indian, 1786 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Case against Miguél Sánchez, Indian, belonging to José Jiménez Solano, for fighting with Jacinto Roque, 1786 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Case against José María Meneses for murdering Cipriano, 1789 - 1790 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Case against Felipe Aldana, Baltazar Dávila Quintero, and Joaquín Blanco, for murdering and robbing the entire family of Joaquín Antonio Dongo, 1789 - 1833 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Case against the Subdelegate of Tepexi de la Seda for illicit friendship with the wife of Pascual Licona, denounced by the latter, 1790 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Investigation of the drowning of the late Salvador Antonio Cardero, 1791 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Case against José Ilario Peréz, for uxoricide to María Inés Apresa, 1791 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Case concerning seizure of tobacco from subjects, 1791 (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Santiago Sebastián vs. Juan Rodríguez, for injury, 1792 (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Petition to the Governor by Francisco de la Fuente, lawyer asking permission to conclude the case against Antonio Chávez, for injury, 1793 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - María Martínez vs. José Guillén, her husband, for adultery, 1794 (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - José Mazera, Indian vs. María de los Dolores Torres, his wife, for adultery, 1794 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Angela de Porras vs. Pedro de Santiago, for raping her daughter, 1795 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Ana Gertrúdis Guerta vs. José Antonio, for injury, 1796 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Rosa María López, Indian vs. José García, for raping Antonia Gertrúdis, 1796 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - Juan Antonia Mena, Indian vs. those who tied him up and injured him, 1796 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Petition by José Mesía that Pedro Antonio Arentigui be released from prison, 1796 (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - José María Rojas vs. Sargent Suniga, for calumny, 1796 (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Petition by Domingo Santiago that his wife be released from prison, having had reason to injure Juan Santiago, 1796 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Investigation of injuries to José Ignacio Bueno and José Marcos Flores, resulting in the death of the former, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Petition that José Nicolás Martínez and others be released from the Royal Prison, 1797 (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Petition by Rafael Cristano that he be released from prison, 1790 (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - Rosa Ortega vs. José María Conchoso, her husband, for carrying out an affair with Casimira de Sirila, 1798 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - José Santiago vs. Diego Santiago, for theft of cows, 1798 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - Petition by Mateo Simón Torija and José Mariano Sánchez that they be released from prison, 1798 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - Manuel de Leon Coronado, Spaniard vs. a drunkard, for injury, 1799 (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - Petition concerning the case against Anastasio Tapia, accused of injuring Julián Mejía, 1799 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Bárbara Sánchez vs. a man who beat Manuel Tejedor, her husband, in their store, 1800 June 6 (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Investigation of the murder of the late Francisco Rojas, 1801 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - Juan Cabrera vs. Francisco Alvarez, for injuries, 1802 (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - Summary of case against Vicente Chango and José Xolulyan, for theft, 1802 (Box 6, Folder 135)
  - María Josef Lon vs. her husband, Manuel Flores, for concubinage with María Toro, 1802 (Box 6, Folder 136)
  - Case concerning excesses of Mariano Ignacio Mercado, imprisoned in Puebla, 1803 - 1804 (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - Investigation of the flight of José Pavía, 1803 - 1807 (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - Petition by Francisco Hernández, imprisoned for violating María de la Luz, that he be set at liberty, 1804 (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - Case against Juan Chávez and others, for murdering José Antonio Herrera, 1804 - 1805 (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - Investigation of a corpse found in the San Antonio River, 1805 (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - Case against José Vásquez, mayor, for freeing a defendant and showing disrespect to the judge, 1805 (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Investigation of the death of José Villegas from a head wound, 1805 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Nicolás María de Veytia vs. Francisco Xavier Gómez Pavino, for injuries, 1806 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Case against Tomás de la Cruz Rostro, Governor of Tierranueva, for insulting the judge, 1807 (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Decree by governor of Puebla concerning the arrest of José Galeote, thief, 1808 (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Francisco Escalera vs. Máximo Domínguez, for insult and intent to murder, 1809 (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - José Manuel Ramos vs. Nicolás Parraga, for injuries, 1810 (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Case against Martín Aparicio, 1811 (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Case against José Ignacio Mariano Aguilar, alias, "Ojos de Achón,", 1811 (Box 7, Folder 150)
  - Case against José María Benítez, for insurgency, 1811 (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Case against María Silvería, Manuel Bautista, Teodoro Castillo, and Lucas Hernández, for murdering Jacinto Maríano Espinoza, 1811 - 1827 (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - Case against Mariano Martínez for injuries to Manuel Mateos, 1812 (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - Investigation of injuries to Manuel Mateos by Mariano Martínez and Miguél Muñoz, 1812 (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Case against Pedro de la Rosa, for treason, 1817 (Box 7, Folder 155)
  - Case against Sargents of Extremadura and a chasseur of the Santo Domingo Batallion, concerning a theft in the division of Cuyunquihuy, 1821 (Box 7, Folder 156)
  - Case against B. Illario de Tapia for harassing José Avila with a firearm, 1821 (Box 7, Folder 157)
  - Case against José María Manrique, for the death of Anita, 1821 - 1824 (Box 7, Folder 158)
  - Case against Rafael Zayas, alias "Coate", for injury to José María Lima and for misconduct, 1822 (Box 7, Folder 159)
  - Case against Mariano de la Trinidad Barreda for injuries causing death of José Antonio Rivera, 1822 - 1825 (Box 8, Folder 160)
  - Case against José María Jaramillo for the murder of Miguél Corona, 1822 - 1826 (Box 8, Folder 161)
  - Case against Carlos Huerta, for theft, 1823 - 1827 (Box 8, Folder 162)
  - The Mayor vs. José Roberto de Jesús Palacio, for murdering his wife, 1824 (Box 8, Folder 163)
  - Case against Vicente Baños and accomplices, for theft, 1824 - 1829 (Box 8, Folder 164)
  - Case against José Augustín de la Rosa Ramos and alleged accomplices, for the murder of José María Peréz, 1824 - 1837 (Box 8, Folder 165)
  - Investigation of the robbery of the store of José Luis Botello, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 166)
  - Case against Manuel Antonio Castañeda, Antonio López, and José Guadalupe López, for robbery, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 167)
  - Case against Francisco Fernández, for the murder of Maríana Gil, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 168)
  - Case against Manuel García, alias "Milpita," for theft, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 169)
  - Case against María Antonia Guadalupe, for injuries resulting in the death of Juana Flores, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Case against Mariano Herrera, Gerbasio Cervantes, and María de Jesús Delgadillo, for robbery, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 171)
  - Case against Florentino José for injuries causing the death of José Nemesio, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 172)
  - Case against José María Masías and José Manuel Assa, for the murder of Juan Gutiérrez, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Case against José María Monje, for fighting with Manuel Fernández, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - Case against Cipriano Morales, for manufacturing gunpowder, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 175)
  - Maríana Ortega vs. Mariano de Orca, mayor of Tehuacán, for abuses, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 176)
  - José Otero vs. Andrés Palacios, for robbing him during the Fiesta de San Sebastián, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - Case against Manuel Rodríguez, alias "Torito", for murdering Nemesio Suárez, 1825 (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - Case against José Mariano del Espíritu Santo, for injury to Manuel Antonio, 1825 - 1828 (Box 8, Folder 179)
  - Case against Manuel Arroyo and María Petra Tepetlapa, for mutual injuries, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 180)
  - Case against Juan Bravo, for theft of tobacco from the National Factory of this State, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 181)
  - Case against Pedro de Jesús, José de la Encarnación, and Andrés de Santa María, for injuries to Manuel de los Santos, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 182)
  - Case against José María Maldonado and Joaquín Torres, for the theft of cattle, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 183)
  - Case against Andrés Martín, murderer of Francisco Rexino, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 184)
  - Case against Mariano Nava, for stealing flour from Pedro Campos and José García de Socaso, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 185)
  - Case against Arcadio Sánchez, for injury to José María Mendoza, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 186)
  - Case against José Antonio de la Torre and Manuel Guerrero, for robbery from José Ignacio de la Torre, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 187)
  - Miguél de la Torre vs. Eligio Fragoso, for theft of pulque, 1826 (Box 8, Folder 188)
  - Case against Juan Antonio and others, for theft from Antonio Díaz, 1826 - 1827 (Box 8, Folder 189)
  - Case against Pedro Ruíz, alias "el tuerto", for loitering and robbing fruit from gardens, 1826 - 1827 (Box 9, Folder 190)
  - Case against Clemente Salazar for injury to Teodosio Filomena, 1826 - 1828 (Box 9, Folder 191)
  - Investigation of complaint against José Albino, 1826 - 1829 (Box 9, Folder 192)
  - Case against Marcos Calderón, for carrying weapons, 1826 - 1829 (Box 9, Folder 193)
  - Case against Diego Nicolás, for carrying a firearm, 1826 - 1829 (Box 9, Folder 194)
  - Case against José Cayetano Villafale, alias "Arenchis", for robbery of abracero, 1826 - 1833, (1898) (Box 9, Folder 195)
  - Case against Rafael Rosette and Felipe Solis, for adultery, 1827 - 1828 (Box 9, Folder 196)
  - Case against José María Castrejón, for theft from the Customs House, Tecamachalco, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 197)
  - Case concerning theft of a mule from Gabriel Ignacio Illescas, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 198)
  - Mayor of San Juan Tlanguizmanalco vs. José Leocadio, for robbery, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 199)
  - Case against José de la Merced and Miguél Gaspar Luna, for theft of a mare, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 200)
  - Case against Tomás Moreno, for injuring Juan Moreno, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 201)
  - Case against José Antonio Rincón, for injury to Domingo Texeda, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 202)
  - Case of the robbery of the Customs house of Tecamachalco, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 203)
  - Petition by Agustín Terrazas that he be released from prison, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 204)
  - Case against Gregorio Agustín Vilchis, for beating his wife, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 205)
  - Case against Julián Zavala, found with a blade inside the prison, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 206)
  - Case concerning information to be obtained from two prisoners, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 207)
  - Case against Cleto Corona, for serious injuries to José Gómez, 1828 - 1829 (Box 9, Folder 208)
  - Case against Mariano Díaz and Antonio Guzmán, for robbery, 1828 - 1829 (Box 9, Folder 209)
  - Case against Manuel Espinoza, for injury to José de la Cruz, 1828 - 1829 (Box 10, Folder 210)
  - Case against Margarita Flores, accomplice to the murder of Maximiliano Rivera, 1828 - 1829 (Box 10, Folder 211)
  - Case against Alejandro García, for theft of material from merchants in the Plaza, 1828 - 1829 (Box 10, Folder 212)
  - Case against José María Gonzáles and José Arcos, for treason, 1828 - 1829 (Box 10, Folder 213)
  - Investigation of whippings ordered by the Mayor of San Juan Tejupa, 1828 - 1829 (Box 10, Folder 214)
  - Case against Albino Soto, for carrying a weapon and other misdemeanors, 1828 - 1829 (Box 10, Folder 215)
  - Case against Diego Toribio and accomplices, for theft, 1828 - 1829 (Box 10, Folder 216)
  - Investigation of the beating of Pedro Alcantara Morales by the Administrator of the Hacienda of Teyecac, 1828 - 1830 (Box 10, Folder 217)
  - Case against José Antonio Gonzáles, for robbery, 1828 - 1830 (Box 10, Folder 218)